A Guide to the Halifax County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1753-1913
Library of Virginia
- 1867-068: Thomas M. Clark and wife vs. Exrs of John Cobbs, etc.:
  According to Carr's affidavit, various slaved in mid-1850s were hired to work for railroad contractors. One slave, Caroline, had a nickname, Tuck. Other slaves had surnames and slaves Jack and Ned were identified as blacksmiths.
- 1868-005: Elizabeth James Murphy aka Elizabeth James Sadler vs. Admr of James Murphy:
  James Murphy was from Ireland and died in Halifax County. He and the plaintiff"s mother were accused of adultery and he was married to another woman at the time. Plaintiff is claiming that she is entitled to James Murphy's estate because she is a blood relative - in an act passed by the General Assembly on 22 March 1851. See also related chancery causes, 1851-004, 1855-030 and 1859-021.
- 1868-011: Albert Satterfield vs. Patrick P. Ryan:
  Debt suit. Plaintiff seeks injunction against defendant regarding gambling debts as the result of placing bets on the U.S. presidential election of 1868.
- 1868-015: Richard Whitlow vs. Martha Whitlow:
  During the Civil War, plaintiff served in the Confederate Army and defendant committed adultery. See related chancery cause 1869-050, in which defendant petitions court and gives a different account of the circumstances surrounding her child, William C.
- 1869-020: Admr of Frances S. Harris vs. Admr of Charles T. Harris, Sr., etc.:
  Decedent, Charles T. Harris, separates from this wife in Virginia and moves to Mississippi where he dies. He owned 32 slaves in Mississippi and 16 slaves in Virginia. His widow makes claims to his estates in both states. Decedent was a Justice of the Peace for Halifax County. Amended suit deals with injunction filed against decedent's administrator. Two slaves named Mary mentioned in record indicate one is yellow and the other black. Slave Cynda had an unsound mind. Slave Dave is identified as an idiot. Decedent sold slaves Charles, and wife Hanner and children, Caroline, Eliza, and Hanner Pernettee, also slave Affa to other to pay bonds to slave traders, Easley, Logan and Company and James Young and Company.
- 1869-021: Heirs of Jesse Ballow vs. Exr of Jesse Ballow, etc.:
  Jesse Ballow died in Cumberland County and was of unsound mind. Cause contends that his will was obtained by fraudulent means. One of plaintiffs in suit, Hudson, was originally a resident of North Carolina. Other defendants in suit resided in Cumberland and Buckingham counties. Cause includes a sale of slaves and a very detailed genealogical chart.
- 1869-033: Heirs of Sally Hart vs. Admr of James Lawson, etc.:
  Cause involves topics of debt, migration, property and slaves. Sally (Sallie) Hart, nee Lawson, died in state of Texas. James Lawson resided in North Carolina. Sally Hart's family moved from Virginia to Missouri and then to Texas. Her oldest son, William Hart, moved to California.
- 1870-014: Admr of Martha F. Medley vs. Elisha Barksdale, Jr., etc.:
  Deceased died in Charlotte County. Plaintiff notes that receipt was destroyed by U.S. soldiers who occupied his home in large numbers during the Civil War. They destroyed his library and some of his papers. A defendant in the suit resides in North Carolina.
- 1870-032: Heirs of Mary Booth vs. Nelson H. Pruden and wife:
  A large, involved estate dispute involving slavery as a central theme. Plaintiff Thomas H. Walthall, according to Josephus Chaffin's deposition, was a cruel overseer. Defendant, Nelson H. Pruden, had been on trial for the murder of slave Serena. Chaffin's deposition outlines in no uncertain terms the cruelties of slavery. See also chancery cause 1875-059.
- 1871-081: John W. Craddock vs. Board of School Trustees for School District of Mt. Carmel Township:
  Plaintiff files injunction against school board trustees and township tax collector to enjoin and restrain them from selling his property for the collection of a tax "to provide school houses, school books and for current school expenses." Plaintiff claims tax is illegal and void due to boundary dispute between townships and have now levied his saddle for sale.
- 1874-009 William G. Pringle vs. Admr of Daniel B. Easley, etc.:
  Cause deals with contract dispute. Suit involves War of 1812 and Mexican War land warrants amounting to 1920 acres. 880 acres were in Iowa and 1040 acres were in Minnesota. See Administrator of Alexander Yuille's answer for details of land warrants. Suit also contains agreement and list of land warrants.
- 1874-010: Legatees of Elizabeth Salle vs. Exr of Elizabeth Salle, etc.:
  Suit involves estate dispute. Some of the defendants reside in City of Richmond and Mecklenburg County. Plaintiffs were formerly the slaves of the deceased, Elizabeth Sallie of Mecklenburg County and were emancipated by her last will and testament. See document "A.S.", filed with amended bill, for additional relationship information and also information on emancipated slaves. See also Mecklenburg Chancery Cause 1860-037.
- 1875-059: Martha T. Pruden by, etc. vs. Nelson Pruden:
  Deals with Divorce/Separate Maintenance. Plaintiff fears her life is in danger. Defendant is beyond cruel to both her and their daughter. He resides with a freed woman, Mary Jennings, and is guilty of adultery. A warrant was issued for his arrest in July 1866 but he has fled the county to "parts unknown." Plaintiff files injunction against defendant so as not to dispose of any of his property which he inherited from the plaintiff when they married. In a deposition from 1872, a witnees stated that the defendant was living in Isle of Wight County. See also chancery cause 1870-032.
- 1876-057: John G. Smith and wife, etc. v. Admr of Alexander Yuille, etc.:
  "Some years before the war, Alexander Yuille removed from the county of Halifax, Va. to the state of Mississippi-leaving in Virginia his evidences of debt and considerable estate of different kinds." He had a cotton plantation with his brother-in-law. Yuille bought a plantation in Mississippi. His market was in New Orleans. He furnished large means in his lifetime to his brother-in-law to speculated in northwestern lands (which belonged to their partnership) located in 45 counties in the states of Kansas, Missouri, Iowa and Minnesota. Most of Yuille's slaves were in Mississippi. Slaves were returned to Virginia. The main defendant resides in the City of Richmond. See also chancery cause 1878-068.
- 1878-043: Widow of Thomas Bruce, etc. vs. Exr of James C. Bruce, etc.:
  Plaintiff describes the personal effects of the late Civil War in running a large plantation - in particular, the emancipation of its slaves. She references the importance of her children's education and her own health (requiring the constant attention of a physician.) Also, plans to rent out her plantations and move to Richmond. See also chancery cause 1881-028 which includes wills of plaintiff's husband and deceased defendant.
- 1878-068: Heirs of Elijah D. Hundley and James A. Henderson vs. Admr of Elijah J. Hundley, etc.:
  Suit involves estate dispute dealing with migration, property and slavery. Elijah D. Hundley also had property in Mississsippi. Mary J. Henderson (formerly Hundley) owned one slave. Dr. William H. Henderson, her husband, was not a resident of Virginia. Heirs of Mary Jane Henderson reside in North Carolina. One of the plaintiffs was the superintendent of his father's cotton plantation in Mississippi. Slaves Israel and Sylvanus worked on the plantation. Also, small corn crop was grown and used on plantation. Excellent insight into running a plantation during the Civil War. See also chancery cause 1877-039.
- 1880-086: Clayton Yancey and wife vs. Alexander Overby, etc.:
  Includes a letter dated 12 June 1860 written by Alexander Overby to his mother Synthy Overby. At the time, Alexander was living in Marshall County, Alabama. He informs his mother of his experience in Alabama.
- 1880-087: Petition of the Guardian of Fanny Mills:
  Application to change the name of Fanny Mills to Fanny Mills Ould.
- 1880-095: George D. Elder, etc. vs. Roanoke Navigation Company, etc.:
  Plaintiffs were businessmen located in Clarksville, Virginia who were reliant on transportation on the on the Dan, Barrister, Staunton, and Roanoke Rivers for their business. They accused the defendants of doing a poor job of maintaining locks and dams and keeping the rivers clear of debris and stones that made navigation difficult and in some place impassable. Yet, the defendants continued to demand the collection of tolls from the plaintiffs. The suit references the increasing use of railroads to transport goods.
- 1881-001: William P. Jones and wife vs. Admr. of Robert Faulkner, etc.:
  Estate dispute case. Numerous references to slaves. Questions in depositions focused on the average price for hiring slaves between 1840 and 1860. Detailed genealogical information concerning the Faulkner, Jones, Redd, Macon, and Halliburton families.
- 1882-047: Admr. of William B. Wills vs. Exr. of Thomas L. Spragins, etc.:
  Estate dispute case. Division of slaves and slave hire accounts used as exhibits. The suit includes a letter that details the ages and health conditions of slaves.
- 1882-062: Jesse Brandon, etc. vs. Sarah Holden, etc.:
  Estate dispute that was originally filed in the 1850's. Exhibits and depositions related to slaves used as exhibits. They describe the sell, value, physical condition, and family relationships of slaves. Individuals in the suit resided in North Carolina. Depositions reference two free African Americans named Stanfield Byrd, a ditcher, and Thomas Day of Milton, NC who was a cabinet maker and undertaker.
- 1883-040: Admr. of Henry Coleman Hamilton vs. Admr. of John Coleman, etc. and Patrick H. Hamilton vs. Edward T. Hamilton, etc.:
  Suit details the impact of the Civil War and its aftermath on the local economy and property values. Depositions related to the value of Confederate money. One deposition includes an exhibit showing the price of gold as compared with Confederate money from May 1861 to April 1865. Deponents spoke of fears felt by local citizens that the Federal Government would confiscate their property (real and personal) during and after the Civil War. Deponents also gave the names of individuals who served in the Confederate army.
- 1883-041: M.W. Fourqurean vs. Admr. of Lucy Boxley, etc.:
  Lucy Boxley died in 1851. The suit involved the distribution of her estate which included slaves. Depositions and exhibits record the names, ages, family relationships, and value of slaves. One deponent, Isaac Banks, was a slave of Colonel W.L. Fourqurean. He was asked questions about the sale and value of slaves.
- 1891-009: George T Yuille, etc. vs. Admr. of Alexander Yuille
  Suit includes extensive list of slave names, including family groupings and ages.
- 1898-073: A.M. Overby vs. Bettie Overby:
  cDivorce case, the husband cites his wife "malformed" female organs as the grounds for his right to request a divorce. His wife's medical condition made it impossible for them to have normal marital relations.
- 1901-008: Laura Canada vs. James E. Canada:
  Divorce suit. Wife Laura Canada seeks divorce from her husband who lived with another woman and left his wife to move to Rhode Island. Court documentation supports her assertion that he left for Rhode Island because there is a grand jury indictment in Rhode Island for James E. Canada. The indictment accuses Canada of fraud charges and minting and distributing counterfeiting coins.
- 1901-028: Pearl K. Lindsay etc., vs. Z.L. Kay, etc.:
  A disabled couple that could not hear or speak entered into a sales agreement with the defendants to sale land thought to be rich in copper and mineral rights. The couple claims the defendants mined the land without authority and pretended to want to buy the land for farming purposes. The attorney memo states the purpose of the suit is to rescind and set aside and annulled the deed of bargain and sale from Pearl and husband Frank to B.P. Atkins and Z.L. Kay. There are additional charges that Kay attempted to commit fraud in an effort to obtain the mineral rich land at a cheap price.
- 1901-036: James H. Powell vs Pauline Powell alias Pauline Thaxton:
  Divorce case. James H. Powell moves to West Virginia to begin a new job leaving his young wife Pauline Powell in Virginia. Powell sends money to his wife for her to move with him to West Virginia, she does not respond to his request. Three years later Powell returns to Halifax and finds his wife has married another man one Killis Thaxton. Pauline's marriage certificate states she married Killis Thaxton in January 1898 and declares her marital status as widowed.